Thank you Greg, Mike, Brittany, for the invitation.
This is my great pleasure to be here to talk about CDD,
and CDD is design technique that we built and we are using at zup, a Brazilian tech company,
to build software - to build real world software. And today my goal here is to convince you that CDD
could be an interesting approach to you for your next product.
So let's just get started with these - these figures here,
which are a lot of code but they all come from the same class,
actually the class from this Spring framework.
If you are a Java developer, chances are that you have used Spring in the past.
So if this kind of thing - this kind of big class happens in Spring,
are well - very well known and popular products - chances are that it may also
happen on our own products and our own projects. And this figure here raised many questions:
how can we refactor, where are the points that we should refactor,
how should we start the refactoring, help spot the bug,
where is the bug, how many bugs,
and how can we test this code to make sure that there is a bug?
And all these questions can be summarized in this simple question here:
so how to reason about this code - so how to understand this code?
So the idea of CDD is to provide a way to improve how developers understand and reason about code.
Last year, I guess, Kent Beck, who is a well-known practitioner,
wrote these tweets that I would like to just read very briefly for you.
"The goal of software design is to create chunks or slices that fits into the human mind."
So going back to the last slide, can we fit that one single class on our mind?
I bet we can do. "Software keeps growing
but the human mind maxed out so we have to keep chunking and slicing differently."
So if you happen to have to leave, to stop early, this is the mess that I'd like to to show to you.
The goal of software is to keep chunking and slicing differently.
CDD is actually another approach - our simple approach - for chunking and slicing.
This is the goal of CDD. And how does this happen with CDD?
Has two goals. The first one is to
reduce the developers' cognitive load. So going back to our first example,
how can we really understand that code?
How much effort should we place to understand that one single class?
Maybe some good effort. And how does CDD
try to reduce this cognitive load? It does so by posing a limit on the
number of items that developers could use in a single class or a single file.
So essentially, you can use whatever
technique or approach that you - you want, you find fun to use, you like to use,
but you should do that with a limit. And CDD brings this idea of limits from this
theory - from this psychological theory, which is the magical number seven theory.
It's a well-known and well-accepted theory from the psychological domain.
And very briefly this theory says that we as human beings are only able to process, like, seven plus
or minus two - minus two units of information in our short-term memory.
If we receive - if we receive more information at the same time,
chances are that we lose our ability to process that information.
So this graph here pretty much shows what - what goes on when we receive more information.
If you are processing just one, two, or three informations at the same moment,
we can handle a very good understanding about what is going on.
But when we receive four, five, six, seven, units of information at the same time,
we drastically reduce our ability to process that information.
That happens when we are trying to give a talk and my kid is calling me,
my phone is beeping, the - the the car is
honking on the streets, and so on, and I eventually lose my ability to
understand what what I was doing. So CDD has this idea of limits.
We should place a limit on the items in the source code that developers could use.
And if a given class or a given file is over that limit it's time to refactor.
So CDD has two main benefits here. It shed some light on the
complexity of the source code and it gives to the developer a tool that is useful to decide
when to refactor - when do we factor? We refactor when you are over the limits.
So here on the right I just have here an example of a single class
that uses CDD by using these ICP annotations. So every time that I'm using this class here
that I suppose increase the complexity - that the teams believes that
could increase the complexity - we should add this annotation here,
ICP, ICP,
ICP. At this moment
we should do that manually and the team is - is in charge of summing all these annotations here
to make sure that the code is over or not the limits.
So this is the idea of CDD, basically it is,
you should go to the your team, talk to the team about,
hey, we have a lambda expression here,
if we use a lot of lambda expression would this increase the complexity of code?
If so, we should now tag these lambda expressions.
We have an if statement here. If we use a lot of if statements,
would this increase the complexity? If yes,
we should now tag this if statement. If we use certain kind of classes,
certain kind of variables, from certain kind of objects,
would this increase the complexity? If so,
we should flag this element. So this is the objective:
you should flag the elements that increase the complexity
and if it's over the budget or limits budget, you should refactor.
So the last part of the talk I just would like to show to you
our experience on using to build Handora. Handora is this training platform
that we built at Zup and Zuppers go there
to learn new technologies, new frameworks, and so this platform is built using four five
servers - sorry five services, and you - we have used CDD to
build three of these services here. So I have a couple of slides here left
and I just would like to show to you this which I believe is the most interesting one.
So here I have a figure when the red line means the average number - size of the classes
and the blue line means the number of classes. So through our software evolution we are
increasing the number of classes in the product. It makes sense because software is growing
so we are also growing the number of classes that we have in the product.
However on the other hand we have this red line here which says that the number of classes -
the size of classes in terms of length of codes - increases in the beginning,
but at some time it does not increase that much - it started to flatten at some
moment - at some time. And this thing here is
what we believe is one of the benefits of CDD. Although we are increasing - almost linearly
increasing the number of classes in the product, the size in terms of lines of code
are not increasing at the same speed - at the same growth of the number of classes,
they are more or less stable.
This also says that - this figure also says that although we do have a small number of sizes,
we do also have some sizes that are a bit over the limits,
so we do have the limits, but we also understood that
for some kind of classes - domain classes - we may not have that limits very well done.
Another figure that I want to show to you is about this study,
which says that developers should strive to keep their methods under 24 lines of code.
And we did a an experiment to make sure - to understand whether this product is under or above
this threshold that the paper suggested. And we notice that 92% of the methods
of this product are under this limits. So even though developers were not taught to, hey,
write small methods because of that paper, they eventually using CDD achieve it - the
same goal of having the small methods. When talking to one of the developers,
they said that every unit of code is impacted because we know that the limit is
and what goes into that limit, so the limit is for the classes and
also the methods are impacted. Finally,
you also understood that CDD could also impact the size of methods, the testing methods,
and in this case we noticed that on average that is 80 lines of code per testing method
and Handora has a good coverage, so generally speaking,
is - we also suggest that CDD could also impact the size of the testing methods.
Therefore what we learned so far is that this seems to help to design these small classes.
CDD also seems to help designing small methods and small testing methods
but as we showed to you,
there is some good effort to use CDD because developers have the flag,
the annotation in the source code. We wrote some static analysis tools
but we understood that the two should be - should be very well integrated with the IDES
otherwise developers will not use them - the tools.
And we also try - we are also trying to motivate other teams to use CDD and,
because of time management and time pressure from their agendas,
it's not easy to adopt and to understand. With this I close my talk and I would be happy
to answer your questions. Thank you.
All right - thank you very much Gustavo, we do have some questions coming in,
and the first one is, can this CDD concept be
linked to existing easy-to-compute metrics like cyclomatic complexity.
Yeah it could be if you happened to flag the same branches and
things that the cyclomatic metric measures. If you happen to flag the same items it could
be a proxy, but,
as we - as I showed in the example, you can also flag, like,
classes that deal with the databases, classes that deal with the user interface,
so in that case, cyclomatic measures may not help.
Okay, and a similar question,
I'll just read this one out. Surely we must have significantly
under seven things to think about since we need the remaining short-term memory
to actually do the thinking about the problem, so how much - how many things can we have in
the code and still have capacity left over to think about what code to write next?
Yeah right, I - so what
what - what happens in the teams is that the team should decide what part of the code
they should measure, they should flag, right, so if the team decides that only these small
classes here and these other cyclomatic kind of cyclomatic measures should be flagged,
so the team just go for it. So CDD is mostly about what
the teams believe would be important to measure. If they believe there are many things to measure,
like a list of a hundred items,
that will be also hard to understand all the items that should be flagged,
but essentially we tell to the teams that they should measure like, five to six to seven items.